[{"question":"In fibrous proteins, polypeptide chains are held together by","a":"van der waals forces","b":"electrostatic forces of attraction","c":"hydrogen bonds","d":"covalent bonds","hint":"","correct":"c"},{"question":"The a-D glucose and 3-D glucose differ from each other due to difference in carbon atom with respect to its ","a":"conformation","b":"configuration","c":"number of OH groups","d":"size of hemiacetal ring","hint":"","correct":"b"},{"question":"Glucose on prolonged heating with Ill gives:","a":"n-Hexane","b":"1-Hexene","c":"Hexanoic acid","d":"6-iodohexanal","hint":"","correct":"a"},{"question":"Denaturation of proteins leads to loss of its biological activity by","a":"Formation of amino acids","b":"Loss of primary structure","c":"Loss of both primary and secondary structures","d":"Formation of amino acids","hint":"","correct":"d"},{"question":"The symbols D and L. represent","a":"the optical activity of compounds.","b":"the relative configuration of a particular stereoisomer.","c":"the dextrorolatory nature of molecule.","d":"the levorotatory nature of molecule","hint":"","correct":"b"},{"question":"Primary structure of a protein is","a":"sequence in which a-amino acids are linked to one another","b":"the folding patterns of polypeptide chains","c":"the pattern in which the polypeptide chains are","d":"the pattern in which the polypeptide chains are aranged","hint":"","correct":"a"},{"question":"Proteins are condensation polymers of","a":"A-amino acids","b":"B-amino acids","c":"a-hydroxy acids","d":"B-hydroxy acids","hint":"","correct":"a"},{"question":"Which of the following is correct about H-bonding in nucleotide?","a":"A-Aand T-T","b":"G-TandA-C","c":"A-Gand T-C","d":"A-Tand G-C","hint":"","correct":"d"},{"question":"Enzymes take part in a reaction and","a":"decrease the rate of a chemical reaction","b":"increase the rate of a chemical reaction","c":"both (a) and (b)","d":"None of these","hint":"","correct":"b"},{"question":"Insulin production and its action in human body are responsible for the level of diabetes. This compound belongs to which of the following categories?","a":"An enzyme","b":"A hormone","c":"A co-enzyme","d":"An antibiotic","hint":"","correct":"b"},{"question":"The function of DNA in an organism is","a":"to assist in the synthesis of RNA molecule","b":"to store information of heredity characteristics","c":"to assist in the synthesis of proteins and polypeptides","d":"all of these.","hint":"","correct":"d"},{"question":"Chromosomes are made from","a":"proteins","b":"nucleic acids","c":"proteins and nucleic acids","d":"carbohydrates and nucleic acids","hint":"","correct":"c"},{"question":"Proteins are found to have two different types of secondary structures viz. a-helix and B-pleated sheet structure. a-helix structure of protein is stabilised by.","a":"peptide bonds","b":"van der Waal's forces","c":"hydrogen bonds","d":"dipole-dipole interactions","hint":"","correct":"c"},{"question":"Which of the following statements is not true about glucose","a":"It is an aldohexose","b":"On heating with HI it forms n-hexane","c":"It is present in furanose form","d":"It does not give 2, 4-DNP test","hint":"","correct":"c"},{"question":"DNA and RNA contain four bases each. Which of the following bases is not present in RNA?","a":"Adenine","b":"Uracil","c":"Thymine","d":"Cytosine","hint":"","correct":"c"},{"question":"Which of the following is not a characteristics of fibrous proteins ?","a":"In the fibrous proteins, polypeptide chains are held together by hydrogen and disulphide bonds.","b":"These have fibre like structure.","c":"These are generally soluble in water.","d":"These have elongated shape.","hint":"","correct":"c"},{"question":"Curdling of milk is an example of","a":"breaking of peptide linkage","b":"hydrolysis of lactose","c":"breaking of protein into amino acids","d":"denaturation of proetin","hint":"","correct":"d"},{"question":"Which of the following statement is true?","a":"Epimers are also anomers","b":"Anomers are also epimers","c":"Both of the above statements are true","d":"Neither of the two statement is true","hint":"","correct":"b"},{"question":"Which one is the absolutely specific term?","a":"A diastereomer","b":"An epimer","c":"An anomer","d":"None of the three.","hint":"","correct":"d"},{"question":"The two forms of D-glucopyranose obtained from the solution of D-glucose are better called","a":"isomers","b":"anomers","c":"epimers","d":"enantiomers","hint":"","correct":"b"},{"question":"The incorrect statement among the following is","a":"a-D-glucose and B-D-glucose are anomers.","b":"a-D-glucose and B-D-glucose are enantiomers.","c":"Cellulose is a straight chain polysaccharide made up of only B-D-glucose units.","d":"The penta acetate of glucose does not react with hydroxylamine.","hint":"","correct":"d"},{"question":"Complete hydrolysis of starch gives:","a":"glucose only","b":"galactose and fructose in equimolar amounts","c":"glucose and galactose in equimolar amounts","d":"glucose and fructose in equimolar amounts","hint":"","correct":"c"},{"question":"Benedict's reagent is reduced by which type of carbohydrates?","a":"Acetals","b":"Hemiacetals","c":"Glucose pentaacetate","d":"None of the three","hint":"","correct":"d"},{"question":"AD-carbohydrate is:","a":"Always dextrorotatory","b":"Always laevorotatory","c":"Always the mirror of the corresponding L-carbohydrate","d":"None of these.","hint":"","correct":"a"},{"question":"Rapid interconversion of a-D-glucose and B-D-glucose to solution is known as:","a":"racemization","b":"asymmetric induction","c":"fluxional isomerization","d":"mutarotation","hint":"","correct":"c"},{"question":"At iso-electric point:","a":"conc. of cation is equal to conc. of anion","b":"Net charge is zero.","c":"Maximum cone, of di-polar ion (Zwitter ion) will be present","d":"All of the above","hint":"","correct":"b"},{"question":"Which of following amino acid has lowest iso-electric point?","a":"Glycine","b":"Alanine","c":"Aspartic acid","d":"Lysine","hint":"","correct":"c"},{"question":"All of the following Statements apply to proteins except ","a":"Proteins generally have no definite melting point","b":"Proteins contain the grouping -CONH-","c":"Proteins can only contain the elements C. H. O and N.","d":"Proteins have high molecular weight","hint":"","correct":"b"},{"question":"Glycosidic linkage is actually an:","a":"Carbonyl bond","b":"Ether bond","c":"Ester bond","d":"Amide bond","hint":"","correct":"b"},{"question":"Among the following organic acids, the acid present in rancid butter is:","a":"Pyruvic acid","b":"Lactic acid","c":"Butyric acid","d":"Acetic acid","hint":"","correct":"c"},{"question":"A strongly alkaline solution of a monoaminodicarboxylic acid contains how many basic groups?","a":"1","b":"2","c":"3","d":"4","hint":"","correct":"c"},{"question":"A mixture of two amino acids having pl 9.60 and 5.40 can be separated","a":"by adjusting the pH of the solution at 9.60","b":"by adjusting the pll of the solution at 4.20","c":"by adjusting the pH of the solution at 7.0","d":"by adjusting the pH of the solution at 7.5.","hint":"","correct":"a"},{"question":"Among the following, the essential amino acid is","a":"Alanine","b":"Valine","c":"Aspartic acid","d":"Serine","hint":"","correct":"b"},{"question":"Observation of \"Ruhemann's purple\" is a confirmatory test for the presence of","a":"Starch","b":"Reducing sugar","c":"Protein","d":"Cupric ion","hint":"","correct":"c"},{"question":"Which of the following protein destroys the antigen when it enters in body cell?","a":"Antibodies","b":"Insulin","c":"Chromoprotein","d":"Phosphoprotein","hint":"","correct":"a"},{"question":"The couplings between base units of DNA is through","a":"hydrogen bonding","b":"electrostatic bonding","c":"covalent bonding","d":"van der Waal's forces","hint":"","correct":"a"},{"question":"When adenine is attached to ribose sugar, it is called adenosine. To make a nucleotide from it, it would require","a":"oxygenation","b":"addition of a base","c":"addition of phosphate","d":"hydrogenation","hint":"","correct":"c"},{"question":"Which of the following polymer is strored in the liver of animals?","a":"Amylose","b":"Cellulose","c":"Amylopectin","d":"Glycogen","hint":"","correct":"c"},{"question":"Which of the following is correct about H-bonding in nucleotide? ","a":"A-A and T-T","b":"G-TandA-C","c":"A-Gand T-C","d":"A-Tand G-C","hint":"","correct":"d"},{"question":"Which of the following is not present in a nucleotide?","a":"Guanine","b":"Cytosine","c":"Adenine","d":"Tyrosine","hint":"","correct":"d"},{"question":"Which of the following is not present in a nucleotide?","a":"Guanine","b":"Cytosine","c":"Adenine","d":"Tyrosine","hint":"","correct":"a"},{"question":"Which of the following is not present in a nucleotide?","a":"Guanine","b":"Cytosine","c":"Adenine","d":"Tyrosine","hint":"","correct":"a"}]